Why wasn't Japan carved up by the Allies
after World War II? The original plan
was to split the country into four
occupation zones run by the Americans,
the Soviets, the British, and the
Chinese. The island of Hokkaido was even
promised to the Soviet Union. But then
one man said no, General Douglas
MacArthur. As the new Supreme Commander
of Japan, he saw the division plan as a
recipe for chaos and a golden
opportunity for the communists to gain a
foothold. So, he made a decision. He
used the fact that the American military
was the only one on the ground to shut
the other allies out completely. Stalin
was so furious of being shut out that he
prepared his own invasion of Hokkaido.
But he backed down at the last minute.
The United States occupied Japan alone,
turning its mortal enemy into its single
most important military base in Asia for
the coming Cold